A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Cooperative Extension, Master Gardener Program, 1970s-2000s
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Records of the Virginia Cooperative Extension, Master Gardener Program, 1970s-2000s
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
RG 26/2/1
6 Cubic Feet; 5 boxes
This collection contains four boxes of slide sets, some with related scripts, for the Virginia Cooperative Extension's Master Gardener Program. Most materials are undated, but likely date from between the 1970s and early 2000s. Topics include flowers, fruits, vegetables, trees, landscaping, gardening, composting, and careers in horticulture.
Virginia Cooperative Extension (1995-)
Virginia Cooperative Extension Service
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Records of the Virginia Cooperative Extension, Master Gardener Program was transferred to Special Collections in October 2012.
Administrative History
From the Master Gardener Program website:
"The Master Gardener training was created by Extension to meet an enormous increase in requests from home gardeners for unbiased, research-based horticultural information. This increase was a result of the urban and transient nature of modern American life.
"Master Gardeners provide a resource for all Extension program areas and for professionals from many other agencies. They provide communities with locally identified programs, including answers to individual questions via hotlines and plant clinics; radio, newspaper, and computer links; educational programs to meet targeted needs; education for the preservation of historic landscapes; urban tree planting programs; and guidance in making the natural environment accessible to all residents regardless of disabilities, incomes, or where they live."
More information about the Master Gardner Program is available online at the Virginia Cooperative Extension website.
Scope and Content
This collection contains four boxes of slide sets, some with related scripts, for the Virginia Cooperative Extension's Master Gardener Program. Most materials are undated, but likely date from between the 1970s and early 2000s. Topics include flowers, fruits, vegetables, trees, landscaping, gardening, composting, and careers in horticulture.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 14 series by broad topic area. Each series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Series I: Annuals and Perennials
Series II: Careers in Horticulture
Series III: Flowers
Series IV: 4-H
Series V: Fruits and Vegetables
Seires VI: Gardening and Composting
Series VII: Indoor Houseplants and Indoor Gardening
Series VIII: Landscaping and Lawns
Series IX: Pesticides and Fertilizer
Series X: Plants/Trees/Shrubs
Series XI: Pruning
Series XII: Turfgrass Maintenance
Series XIII: Weed Control
Series XIV: Miscellaneous slides
Index Terms
Subjects:
Agricultural extension work; Agriculture; Food Technology and Production; History of Food and Drink
Organizations:
Virginia Cooperative Extension (1995-); Virginia Cooperative Extension Service; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Series I: Annuals and Perennials
  - Annuals for a Shady Location (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annuals Grown for their Colorful Foliage #1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annuals Grown for their Colorful Foliage #2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Introduction to Perennials (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Perennials (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Perennials Adapted to a Dry Location (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Perennials Adapted to Dry Locations (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Perennials Adapted to a Moist Location (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Perennials for Continuous Bloom (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Perennials for Partial Shade (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Perennials for a Sunny Location (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Perennials Grown for their Foliage (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Perennials Suitable for Naturalizing (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Program Annuals (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: Careers in Horticulture
  - Careers in Horticulture #1 (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Careers in Horticulture (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Careers in Horticulture #3 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Master Gardener College Event (1999-2000), 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series III: Flowers
  - AAS Winning Flowers #1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - AAS Winning Flowers (3 folders), 1977-1997 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - Azaleas in the Garden #1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dried Flowers for Arrangements (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Exhibiting and Judging Flowers #1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Exhibiting and Judging Flowers #2 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Flowers (Box 1, Folder 32a)
  - Flower Arrangements for Christmas (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Roses #1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Roses #1, #521 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Wild Flowers (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Wild Flowers of Virginia (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Series IV: 4-H
  - 4H Chesterfield Urban Gardening, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37a)
  - 4H Garden Ecology (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 4H Horticulture Motivational (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 4H Horticulture Slide Set and Record Sheet (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 4H Kitchen Garden Project #1 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 4H Kitchen Garden Project (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 4H Motivational #1 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 4H Mum Project (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 4H Planting Ornamental Trees and Shrubs (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
  - 4H Vegetable Garden Project Original (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - 4H Vegetable Garden Project (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Series V: Fruits and Vegetables
  - AAS and Vegetable Pupes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - AAS: Vegetables, 1977-1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - AAS Vegetables, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Better Nutrition through Family Vegetable Gardens (SI) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dwarf Apples on a Fence (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Home Vegetable Diseases #5 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Home Vegetable Garden Practice (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Judging Fruits and Vegetables (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Judging Fruits and Vegetables #2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Peach and Nectarines (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Proper Management of Fertilizers in Home Vegetable Gardens (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Selected Vegetable Diseases (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Small Fruit Culture: Black Raspberry (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Small Fruit Culture: Red Raspberry (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Small Fruit Varieties and Culture (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Starting Your Own Vegetable Seed (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Strawberry Culture #1, #572 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Strawberry Culture #2 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Minimum Chemical Vegetable Garden (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
  - Tree Fruit in the Home Garden (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Unusual Vegetables for the Home Garden #1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Using Organic Materials int he Vegetable Garden (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Vegetable Gardening for the Beginner (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-29)
  - Vegetable Gardening for the Beginner #3 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Vegetable Gardening for the Beginner #6 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Vegetable Gardening for the Beginner #9 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Vegetable Gardening for the Beginner #11 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Vegetable Insects (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Vegetable Varieties for the Home Garden #1 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Vegetable Varieties for the Home Garden #2 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Series VI: Gardening and Composting
  - Backyard Composting, 1993-01 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Backyard Composting (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 38-40)
  - Biblical Garden (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Composting Slide Set (Original) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Container Gardening (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Container Gardening: Principles and Practices (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
  - Denver Botanic Gardens (Box 2, Folder 45a)
  - Fall and Winter Garden Care (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Fighting Drought in the Home Garden (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Flower Beds and Boarders (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Garden Insects #2 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Gardening in a Small Space #1 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Gardening in a Small Space #2 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Gardening in a Small Space #4 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Gardening in a Small Space #5 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Gardening in a Small Space #6 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Gardening in Small Spaces #2 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Gardening in Small Spaces #10 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Gardening in Raised Beds #1 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Gardening in Raised Beds #3 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Gardening in Raised Beds #4 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Gardening in Raised Beds #5 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Gardening to Encourage Wildlife #1 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Gardening in Small Plots (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Herb Culture for the Home Garden (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Herbs for the Home and Garden #1 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Insects of the Home Garden (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Longwood Gardens (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Longwood Slides (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minimum Chemical Garden #2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Minimum Chemical Garden #3 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minimum Chemical Garden #4 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Minimum Chemical Garden #5 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Rock Gardens (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Water Gardens and Pools #2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Welcome to VCE Master Gardening (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Welcome to VCE Master Gardening, 2001-01 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Welcome to VCE Master Gardening Power Point (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series VII: Indoor Houseplants and Indoor Gardening
  - Flower Arranging for the Home #2 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Flowering Houseplants (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
  - Flowering Houseplants Set #1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Flowering Houseplants Set #4 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Flowering Houseplants Set #5 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Houseplants for the Home (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Houseplants for the Home #3 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Indoor Landscaping (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Indoor Plantscaping (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 25-27)
  - Indoor Plantscaping #2 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Indoor Plantscaping (Copy 3) (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Spring Bulb for Indoor Bloom (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Series VIII: Landscaping and Lawns
  - Calibrating Your Lawn Spreader (8 folders) (Box 3, Folder 31-38)
  - Calibrating Your Lawn Spreader #2 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Construction of a Dry Wall (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
  - Focus on Nozzles (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Ground Covers in the Landscape #1 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Ground Covers in the Landscape #4 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Landscape (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Landscape Tree and Fertilization (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Landscape Tree and Shrub Fertilization (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Landscaping for Outdoor Living (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Landscaping for Year Round Interest (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Landscaping for the Home #2 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Water Quality and Landscaping (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 51-55)
- Series IX: Pesticides and Fertilizer
  - Applying Pesticides Safely for the Environment (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 56-58)
  - Insects Indoors (Box 3, Folder 58a)
  - Landscape Tree and Shrub Fertilization (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Pesticide Safety (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Proper Management of Fertilizer in Home Gardens (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Proper Management of Fertilizer in Home Vegetable Gardens (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 2-6)
  - Proper Management of Fertilizer in Home Vegetable Gardens #2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Proper Management of Fertilizer on Home Lawns (11 folders) (Box 4, Folder 8-18)
  - "Protecting Water Quality Through Proper Pesticide Use" Multimedia Kit (including VHS) (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Reading and Understanding the Pesticide Label for the Home and Garden (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Understanding Pesticide Labels (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Series X: Plants, Trees, and Shrubs
  - Concepts of Ornamental Disease (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Concepts of Ornamental Disease Identification (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Deciduous Specimen Trees (O.S) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Drawing for Slide Sets (originals and 1 copy each) (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Grafting #1 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Herbaceous Ornamental Plants (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Large Tree (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Lists of Plant Materials for Special Uses (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Plant Ailments (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Plant Propagation (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 30-32)
  - Plant Propagation #4 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Plant Windows (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Plants Changing Man's Environment (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Plants for Hanging Baskets (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Plants that Withstand Adverse Conditions (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
  - Shrubs (Box 4, Folder 39a)
  - Shrubs for a Shady Location (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Stress and Salt (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - The Reasons for Planting Shade and Ornamental Trees (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Things Plants Need- Garden Ecology (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Transplanting Techniques for Community Trees (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Winterizing Your Trees and Shrubs (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 44-45)
  - Winterizing Your Trees and Shrubs #5 (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Series XI: Pruning
  - Pruning: Principles and Practices (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
  - Pruning: Principles and Practices (Missing Slide # 3, 15, 17, 42, and 59) (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Pruning Shrubs and Trees (Box 4, Folder 50)
- Series XII: Turfgrass Maintenance
  - Turfgrass Establishment (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 51-52)
  - Turfgrass Establishment Master Gardener (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Turfgrass Maintenance (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 54-58)
- Series XIII: Weed Control
  - 20 Common Weeds of Virginia Gardens (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - 20 Common Weeds of Virginia Gardens #1 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - 20 Common Weeds of Virginia Gardens #2 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Weed Control in Your Garden (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Weed I.D. (Box 4, Folder 63)
- Series XIV: Miscellaneous slides
  - Miscellaneous slides (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 3-6)
    Scope and Content
    This collection included a large group of slides that were not identified or located with other slides sets/scripts. A small percentage have notes on them, but most are not labeled. These slides have been put in sleeves, but are not arranged in any particular order.